Hello guys. Am I alive? Hello guys. Am I
alive? Good morning and good evening
everyone. Check audio. Check video.
Check.
Okay. So, today I'm going to do random.
You are watching Xa talk show where a
tech nerd talks random stuff.
Usually about programming and
mathematics, computer stuff, okay?
And today's topic
there's nothing really. I'm just going
to talk random because I haven't done a
live stream for a while, for a week, I
think.
And you can join my Xa Discord. Uh we
got interesting people, but it's dead.
Because of the internet halt theory.
Okay, let me close my door.
Internet halt theory, which is a theory
I came up.
Uh which basically means beginning
around mid-2025,
there is a
human interaction stopped on the
internet.
Or rather,
massively drastic drastically reduced
human interaction on on the internet.
For example, on Twitter or YouTube
comments, you know, any any of uh human
interaction. Beginning around mid-2025.
That's my theory, which I call it
internet halt theory.
And this is very much tied to AI. So, AI
uh about beginning about this year,
which made me depressed. If you watched
my video live stream, you know, you
know, I talked about it.
Uh and I you know, so so so it it's tied
with the AI stuff. Because AI has
massively changed humanity, okay? In a
significant way because I like I said
it is like you have, you know,
multitudes.
One aspect, one of the many aspects is
that you have the like a professor
around the clock for every each person
on Earth or at least half of the person,
which means 4 billion.
So, it's like you have 10 professors
serving as your private tutor
around the clock anytime you want, any
topic on chemistry, on sciences, on
physics, on mathematics, on programming,
on any programming language, on any
esoteric detail programming language
uh community such as JavaScript, React,
you know, lots of those things
which I'm going to talk about today,
okay? And if you are here, say hi, okay?
I'd love to you must comment, okay?
Okay, comment at the comment place.
And where we begin in the beginning.
Okay, so you look at my website,
beautiful ksaldi.code, okay?
ksaldi.info. So, you go down, go down.
So, which uh I'm going to talk about web
dev, a lot of web dev
uh today, especially uh especially
JavaScript history, okay? So, I'm going
to talk about a lot about the huge this
I spent like 4 hours on this article
today.
The history of JavaScript uh 30 years of
So, in a sense, this history of
JavaScript is a view of the computing
industry beginning in 1997. I mean, 1995
so or 1996, okay? Anyway, roughly 30
years of computing history we can see
via JavaScript or in general in general
web dev.
So, anyway, I I I started to talk about
stuff, okay? So, I was going to say
yeah, so AI so AI so internet whole
theory which which is about
my I you know, I feel that beginning mid
around mid-2025 there is a stoppage of
human interactions. Okay, then and
uh
um
you know, so [snorts] it kind of that's
my internet whole theory which is tied
to AI because AI is changing humanity
beginning I would say like beginning in
2026 that's the milestone. Not before.
You know, maybe maybe it maybe 2025 but
basically 2025 and 26 that's the
beginning of AI changing humanity. Okay.
That is my view.
Okay, so that that you know, I'm going
to you know, so this is my random uh we
you know, we're going to talk about
random stuff anyway. So you um
So if you are like expecting some like
um
Wait, where did my
Did I close a buffer?
>> [laughter]
>> I think
I I closed the buffer by mistake. So
that is the star command log mode. Okay,
let me start again.
Star start command log mode. Okay, so
then so you can see that's Emacs for
those of you don't know this is Emacs
the powerful text editor. So it shows my
command calls and uh keystroke I type in
real time. So you know, so for example,
I go down, I page up or page down so you
can see the command I call is beginning
of line.
Um
you know, that beginning of line or
block. Fantastic. It's part of star
flight keys. Okay.
Anyway, so
random. Okay.
Now, I love to see your comments. So
comment no comment and donate.
Okay, so so uh so we want to talk about
so we want to talk about a few things,
okay?
So,
um
let's go to JavaScript, my JavaScript
blog, fantastic and beautiful. Now, go
back here
and paste a link here. Now, as we talk,
we're going to add links as a record of
what we talked about.
Okay?
Press, press, press, press, create a new
section, that's a link, remove the to-do
part, and remove the to-do, and also
remove the date, show in browser,
fantastic, web dev, okay? So, let me
start with beginning by talking about
the history of JavaScript, okay?
So, like you know, like I said, it's a
it's like a glimpse of
computing history of past 30 years.
Uh well, I'm not going to go through it
because this really a lot. So,
basically, 1994, Netscape created the
web browser that beats the previous
Mozilla, okay? So, 1994 is
is basically when Internet begin, okay?
1996, JavaScript was born,
written by Brendan Eich,
created in 10 days.
You know, created, implemented,
designed, implemented in 10 days due to
social, I mean, corporate pressure
pressure, okay? So, they have to do it,
you know, it's So, basically, in 10
days. According to Brendan Eich, you
know, that's that's the story, but
you know, you might say, "Okay, 2
weeks." Okay? You know, so pretty short,
or a month. A programming [snorts]
language created in, you know, 10 days
or a month,
that's pretty tough.
So, that's why JavaScript sucks, sucks
donkey ass, okay? Comments, okay? If you
are here, comments, okay? Now, how many
people do I have watch like one? Oh,
Jesus.
Okay, so I'm I'm encouraged because I
met Andy.
Uh I met Andy last week. We had dinner
and Andy told me, "Remember some people
are watching you even when not
uh live."
Okay, so any any anyways, JavaScript is
a suckiest language in one of okay, top
top Well, actually C++ sucks more.
C++ You you got you got few candidates.
C++
PHP
Python
and C, okay. But actually, I think um
PHP and Python are
better than JavaScript. I would say,
okay.
Uh and and so
but C++ I would say worse. Okay, so
JavaScript is not the suckiest language.
C++ is worse.
[ __ ] [ __ ] worse. [ __ ] this C++.
Okay, anyway, JavaScript created in 10
days, 1996.
Then Microsoft introduced JScript.
>> [laughter]
>> You know, "Oh, you created JavaScript.
We going to try to
you know, pick what color is your pants
and we going to create JScript
alternative." 1996, okay, Microsoft.
Reverse engineer, okay. And in 1997,
ECMAScript the standard is was
published, okay, 1997. 1998, Netscape
struggles, you know, they can't fight
JavaScript, you know.
If you are my followers, you know,
typically you're you know, we are in
open source community typically because
that's what where I am. Emacs, Unix,
Linux, you know. I never you know,
although I use Microsoft stuff, but I
never
is part of Microsoft. I don't Microsoft
technology except in the past 10 years I
started to do PowerShell and this year F
sharp. Anyway, I digress. Anyway, so I
always been a Unix people.
Emacs and Unix programming languages,
you know. So anyway, so so so so let's
not get too far. Let's focus, okay? I
want to talk about this history because
this history is going to last
you know, it take can take several hours
to talk about JavaScript history, okay?
So 1996 Microsoft introduced JScript
kind of
uh
reverse engineered it, you know, to
compete. So 1997
ECMAScript, the standard for JavaScript,
was released. Now the name is another
stupid story like ECMA.
>> [laughter]
>> ECMA
[ __ ] idiot.
1998 Netscape struggles and open source
Navigator, the Netscape browser, okay?
Created the Mozilla project which
created Firefox, okay? Which is the
browser you are looking at, okay? This
is Firefox. This is Brave browser. I
highly recommend. This is the Brave
browser, okay? This one. And over here,
that's Google. That don't use Google,
okay? I only use it for Google stuff.
Because they look into your pants,
Google. Became the deep the biggest deep
state. Google runs USA kind of, you
know, like Google runs half of USA. You
know, because well, because USA is a
capitalistic capitalistic state.
You know, which is very good except USA
is corrupt capitalism.
>> [laughter]
>> Capitalism is very good. It's freedom as
opposed to the open source [ __ ]
because open source is communism ideal.
You must give your software free.
If you code it, I must have it, too. You
know, open source by Richard Stallman.
[ __ ] it.
By the way, 30 years ago, I was a
fanatic of Richard Stallman, but
you get old, okay?
So,
okay, I digressed all over. So, so open
source is a communism ideal.
There's no freedom because whatever you
know you I demand whatever you do, I
demand it's mine, too. There's no
ownership.
That's open source. Free software
evolved into open source. They they are
in in war, okay?
So, that's not freedom. Freedom is
free trade. I create something, you want
it, give me money.
Oh, I don't think so. Then, fine, okay?
You pick somewhere else. That's freedom.
Free trade, okay? Capitalism.
But the in
But the USA United States of America
case
uh that can kind of became corrupted, uh
you know, corrupted. So, it's like, you
know,
yeah, you know,
you know, very corrupted. So, a lot
people blame capitalism, and they
promote communism, which I don't think
is right. But then but but actually it's
um a little bit more complicated because
when you run a state, there's many
uh So, this belongs to the area of
political science.
You have to know a bit about the
political science theories and how you
know how do you run a country. What's
what is exactly capitalism? How what you
know, what is communism? We with where
you have the teenager idiots like the
Zumas on Twitter every day telling you,
"Oh, capitalism is good or bad. Oh,
communism is good or is bad. Oh, I I'm a
anarchist is good or bad." [ __ ]
idiots, okay?
So, anyway, this belongs to the
political science, which also is
you know, if you go to universities,
which is fairly corrupted. So, they they
teach you things that's not exactly
right. Anyway, so
So, what I'm saying is basically this
this this isms, okay? You know, like you
don't
This isms are academic theories. You um
They try to summarize what, you know,
the theories and what's going on. But,
it's not like mathematics. You know,
math theory is like it works.
>> [laughter]
>> But, this social sciences is is kind of
fuzzy, okay? So, anyway, a lot of people
young people in USA, we got lots of
problems today. And so, some people
blame the communist. Some people blame
the capitalist, you know,
you know,
it's all wrong. So, in my opinion, it's,
you know, don't focus on that. Focus
just just focus on crime. Just focus on
which politician is lying. If you lie,
you are wrong. Okay, that's it.
Doesn't matter what policies, what, you
know, just don't lie.
So, I mean, of course, don't lie. But,
so, if you see a politician that's
lying, yesterday he's saying that, today
he's saying that, he said he didn't say
that, you know, but there's a video,
then
this
politician should go to jail.
Okay, that's it.
That's my philosophy about you know, how
to run a state, you know,
like the exact policies doesn't matter
that much. Because once you have a
society where people cannot lie, the
moment they lie, they find, you know,
people found out, they go to jail, then
the society will be good.
Okay, that's my opinion. So, you know,
like
you know, that like you we when it comes
to politics, you you got people each
one's got their opinions, you know, they
don't I I don't agree. I think you know,
you know
Anyway, so this is my opinion about
politics, about how to run a country.
Just, you know, you should anyone who
lies should go to jail. How long in jail
depends on the severity of the lie. You
know, so if you go to war where a lot of
people will die because well, you lied
some you know, weapons of mass
destruction.
>> [laughter]
>> Then you should go to jail for good.
That's my opinion, okay?
So I don't be you know, I don't buy you
know, I don't believe the isms like oh,
I believe in socialism.
I I believe in communism.
I believe in capitalism. You know,
I don't believe in no no of that [ __ ] or
or anarchist [ __ ] Or liberalism.
Actually
Actually I was a liberal um Wait, how do
you call Wait, also also the naming of
these phrases
uh is different depending on where you
from because in Europe when you say
liberalism, they think of one thing. But
in USA when you say the same thing, the
same term, they think another thing. So
it's very different, okay?
Like [clears throat] so uh
libertarianism.
So when I was young, I would say I was
liber- libertarianism, okay?
Which I'm I'm still kind of more more of
a libertarianism.
Uh
um kind of person. Okay, so I'm not you
know, I'm not exactly the conservative.
I'm not a god believer. I'm not a you
know, god believer. Depending on which
god you know, like which god you know,
like for example in America when you say
god believer, of course of course that's
great Christianity. We must believe that
you know, they fighting the left you
know, right party and left party.
But on the uh in um
But of course, there is
the God from Islam and there's a God
from another country kind of in Middle
East. So, they disagree, okay? Like God,
what which one?
You have to say like which one?
So,
so okay, so so so you know, so it you
know, it's it's you know, they they they
they
uh you know, they they they disagree not
just that they disagree, but they do
things, you know, it's very bad.
This this God-believing.
Anyway, so back to So, I was saying so
Netscape struggles open source Net open
source Navigator. That's the first open
source from a big corporation. That's
the beginning of the
the movement of the open source
communism ideology, which gave us today
the deep state, Google, Facebook,
Microsoft. Bigger than ever.
And they are also the biggest
the
uh code supporter of open source. For
example, you know, yeah.
You know, but but they are the they they
are the most evil, but they are the
funders. They are the foundation of open
source after 20 years, okay? From
because in my opinion, it's from this
communism ideology.
Okay, I so I recommend you don't believe
in any ideology.
Well, but you cannot help it because
every each person when we were born, we
don't know nothing.
We start from fresh, you know, know
nothing.
Like today, you know, like you know
something,
but your younger brother don't know
because he was he was born 2 years later
than you. He doesn't know a thing, you
know, he
but but but but by tomorrow,
there are new person born
that don't know even nothing. He have to
start from the beginning. So, anyway, so
so human animal society, you have this
situation where you have generations.
And I mean, that's natural. That's just
how
things are. So,
so the the the the ideas, the the
beliefs of what you know, you have to
learn from scratch. Like you don't know
what is one one plus one. When did you
learn that?
>> [laughter]
>> Your brother doesn't know. Yeah, but
your brother's son doesn't know. It
was just like forever people don't know.
They have to learn one plus one from
scratch
at some time.
So, you have to learn about, you know,
the ideas of of oh oh free sandwich. Is
it good or bad? Like everyone is
different, so you learn.
So, that's why there's a chaos. So,
there will be oh so the ideology thing
is always very seductive.
You know, a vision. Oh, why can't we
have a, you know, imagine world?
>> [laughter]
>> You know, like that John Lennon song.
How beautiful. Imagine a world is
you know, peaceful, no religion, no
country, everyone lives in peace. Like
yeah, like a [ __ ] fat [ __ ]
You know, so in my opinion, if you
believe in that that John Lennon song,
that's when you have
that's when you will have like
um how shall I say? You know, how shall
I say? I don't want to say something
where YouTube bans me.
But
uh politic uh imagine, okay, the song is
called imagine. Give peace a chance,
working class hero, jet what?
Imagine, okay,
John Lennon song Imagine.
I'm not going to play it because the
moment you play it for a few seconds,
YouTube is going to
censor your YouTube saying you you
infringed on copyright, okay?
You know, so John Lennon has this song,
you know, beautiful song.
But
so I would say in my opinion this you
know
this is kind of you believing in that,
that's where
your society start to do some things
evil, okay? When you when you when you
believe in this
>> [music]
>> kind of thing, okay?
I don't want to play it because like I
play it for a few seconds, Google is not
going to flag your video for copyright
infringement.
Okay, so I was you know I I I rambled
for how long for
um
20 minutes and we didn't talk about
anything about JavaScript history. So
anyway, I was talking about Netscape's
struggles. Released open source
navigator their browser, okay?
And that's communism, the beginning of
open source movement, okay? Then
Microsoft released Internet Explorer 5
and JS start got released, okay? So
anyway, so this is article
of history of JavaScript. Now, the
original article is from Deno. Deno I
highly recommend, okay? Deno is this
JavaScript compiler, also do TypeScript.
I highly recommend. So they have article
30 years of JavaScript, okay?
History of JavaScript. So they have a
nice article, you know, 1994, 95. So you
can see the Netscape browser, I used it,
you know.
Netscape browser browser looks like
that. Netscape. Netscape navigator,
okay? So they you know, so
>> So, anyway, so they have articles. So,
go read it, okay? You can go read it.
Brendan Eich is on Twitter. Brendan Eich
is one of the guy who is like like
typically when you are a programmer, but
when you get old like 40, you get
married or you become a you know
managers. You run a corporation. You
stop coding. You stop coding. You you
became like the suits.
But a few hackers are different. Brendan
Eich is one of them.
He is still on Twitter,
you know, arguing about programming
languages like you know you
>> [laughter]
>> Brendan Eich, okay? Brendan Eich let's
let's go to his um
you know, Brendan Eich is still on
Twitter everyday and mostly posting
arguing sometimes argue. He is also
argumentative. Arguing about programming
language or stuff. Um so let's see
so let's see Brendan Eich
the creator of JavaScript, okay? Uh so
let's see my Twitter uh you cannot see,
okay? So, let me magnify.
Uh wait.
Wait. Why why is my What?
Okay.
Magnify. Magnify. Magnify.
MAGNIFY.
NOW, LET'S SEE WHERE, OKAY? OKAY, big
enough?
Comments, okay? If you
if you guys are here comment.
So, Brendan Eich is saying um so I I
just wanted to show you a Brendan Eich.
So, that's a JavaScript history. No, I
was talking about something else, but um
yeah, Brendan Eich, okay? So, Brendan
Eich you can uh you can follow him, of
course. He's the creator of the Brave
browser, which is the browser you are
looking at right now. Fantastic. And I
use Brave search all the time. Brave
search.
Uh let's see what AI is the best.
Okay, Brave search.
Also got a AI, fantastic. Because I use
it frequ- frequently every day or
basically every day. And I also ask
Google. So anyway, so Brendan Eich,
okay, he's a nerd.
He's still, you know,
posting and stuff. So anyway, that's
Brendan Eich. So so I just want to tell
you about these JavaScript articles,
okay? Great article, go read it.
Uh it's, you know, it's pretty long.
It's pretty long, so it's from 1990 30
years 30 years of JavaScript.
Uh so it's it's like I said, it's a
glimpse of computing history. You can
see the
uh ebb and flow, you know, history the
you know, the the ons and offs and, you
know, the the the happenings, okay?
Of the coding industry focus on the web,
okay? Mozilla Firefox was born there.
Apple introduced Safari Safari, you
know, browser Apple.
And
killed the flash.
You know, so that's a thing. Uh Gmail,
the beginning of Gmail
giant from Google.
You know, like let me tell you a story.
Like you know, when Gmail began on the
web, you know, I was thinking and a lot
of people like we are thinking, "What an
idiot."
Who's going to
you know, use
um
you read email on browser.
I mean, you have dedicated uh email
applications, you know, like like
you can you can read emails in Emacs.
Okay, you just type uh
Rmail. Rmail is one of one There are a
few, okay? Rmail is one of them. So you
press that, you can read email. Okay,
but I haven't set it up, okay?
So you can in email in other in in many
applications. Like before there's a web,
you know, application like you have lots
of different email applications. Like
what Why would someone want a web like
reading email in a web browser? Like
idiot. A [ __ ] [ __ ] idiot. And
also, of course, it's super slow because
back then you don't have like JavaScript
like today. You don't have React, you
don't have all that. So, this is this
you know, Gmail is 2004.
It's like a basically the first
kind of big application, Gmail, okay, on
the web.
So, Google is doing that and and I
thought like who who the [ __ ] do use
that do that?
But, of course, today things are
different. Today is like nobody use
anything else. Web You go to web to read
email email. That's about it. Well,
on your phone these days.
Okay, so Gmail was born 2004.
Anyway, this is this a lot of history,
okay? So, I I'm not going to go over it
30 years of history. So, um nobody is
watching my video, okay?
So, what I'm going to do? I think I'm
going to stop talking.
Um
Uh I rambled over.
Uh it's kind of sad because these days,
you know,
you do a live stream, nobody is here and
uh
Uh I'm And by the way, it's not just me.
Like most people like well, a lot like
uh professors, for example. Great
professors. You you do a live stream,
nobody watches.
Um
because I've seen professors I know. You
you go watch, you know, you look at
their YouTube like, "Oh, 100 100 views."
>> [laughter]
>> Uh much even less than me.
So, um
And then today, you know, so I was
looking at, you know,
like the web history. So,
you know, I so I was I you know, I
talked to AI a lot. I asked AI about the
internet whole theory. Is it true that
people's in- human interactions on the
internet decreased drastically? It is
true. Like because for example, YouTube,
you know, YouTube today they have like
millions of accounts automated
uploading AI-generated videos, millions
account like like just suspended.
So
that's why so YouTube like YouTube is
like dead. I mean, it's it's massive.
You got more and more videos, but like
there's little
you don't see human anymore. It's like
it's like just just just the all fake
[ __ ]
That's that's the situation. And when I
do live stream, you know, so
you know, like right now six views.
Where are you? I don't know who you are.
So,
yeah, that's the situation, but it's not
just because I think you know, so it's I
think that's overall happening, okay.
So
uh
Okay, so what what we going to do? So we
talked about JavaScript
history, so that article, okay. So copy
the link back to Emacs.
Uh paste it here.
Paste so you are looking at my Emacs
workflow showing browser, so you can see
I got the link.
So this article, so so you can read on
the Deno website, John Resig created
jQuery, okay. Uh so a lot video and and
2007, iPhone was created, Apple, Steve
Jobs.
Uh 2007, Netscape shut down its
navigator. Yeah, it's dead. The the the
ending of browser was, okay. Douglas
Crockford create published JavaScript
the good parts. Douglas Crockford is a
giant in a JavaScript community. He He
He He created JSON, okay?
Uh you know, Google Chrome Google
released Google Chrome 2008. Google
Chrome was was born this this browser,
okay?
Then
uh anyway, so so anyway, so I'm not
going to go go through Ryan Dahl 2009.
Node.js was born.
Ryan Dahl is a genius, okay?
I like it. I like him.
Uh then Express.js I don't know too
much. ECMAScript 5
okay, they added
strict.
Anyway, so and CoffeeScript is history.
Nobody use CoffeeScript anymore, not
many.
I think it's still around, but not
Anyway.
So they and the NPM was born 2010.
>> [laughter]
>> Anyway, so Deno
they got an article, so you look for it
a brief history of JavaScript. You'll
find it, okay?
But but I have my own version.
So you go to xsali.info JavaScript so
brief history. So I
kind of borrowed some points from them.
Then I kind of created some like points
milestones, okay? So all these events
some of the their events they included I
removed. So I don't because I don't
consider it important, not to me.
So anyway, but in in my version I have
lots of my own notes. For example, when
JSON you know, I have a tutorial on
JSON.
Kind of short tutorial, okay? So that's
about JSON.
Uh JSON was created the first JSON is
2001.
But I didn't start to use JSON until
like
a few year, you know, until 10 years
ago.
So, anyway, so but some of them I have
my own articles. JavaScript the good
parts, okay? So, that books that book
JavaScript the good parts, I have a
review.
And plus the other book, this this is
the greatest book, okay? Which I include
in my um
in my history. So, anyway, so uh Common
JS module system was, you know, 2009.
Then you have AMD
module system,
2009, too, okay? Then you got um
uh Apache versus Node JS versus Nginx.
And ng- int Nginx, that's 2013, a
hugely popular humor video, okay?
Which I annotated. Very funny, okay?
Because, you know, so you have to you
see
this is history in perspective. So, at
that time,
when when Node JS was born, Node JS
created this thing. So, where is Node
JS? Node JS um
um
Google Gmail uh Ajax, Mozilla released
MDN, jQuery, Apple iPhone, JavaScript
the good parts, okay? 2008. Google
Chrome browser is born, 2008. Common JS
module, 2009.
AMD module system, 2009. Node JS 2009
there, okay? So, when Node JS was
created, the you know, they have this
async thing.
>> [laughter]
>> Async async programming. Like, what the
[ __ ] is async programming?
People are making fun of it. And
programmers don't know it be- because at
that time,
there's no async programming.
Well, there is it it it exist in some
niches, but vast majority of programmers
never heard of. Like what the [ __ ] is a
sync programming?
Very strange. Okay, and so there's a lot
debate, you know, we don't know what it,
you know, exactly
how it is. So so So someone made this
video, very funny, okay? Because at that
time everyone is like, "Oh, you need a
sync. You need a sync. No, we we we we
Node.js beats Apache because a sync."
>> [laughter]
>> A sync.
>> [snorts]
>> A sync is the worst [ __ ] I Later on, I
believe, okay? I have articles. So
anyway, so you look at my Okay, so my my
version annotated um JavaScript history.
So but the parent page is history of web
tech tech. So I have So the first one
Now I just created today, history of
JavaScript. And this page is long, okay?
So it's like um
you know, scroll down uh 10 scroll
downs, so 20 scroll downs.
Okay, at at the bottom I have another
collection of articles related to
JavaScript, okay? All details. But
anyway, you go back to history of web
tech index on sody.info.
You can see so this history of
JavaScript this I created today, but
then there's another about 40 50 pages
of history of the web tech. So for
example, you can see this web badges
history. This this This is around year
2000. So every browser uh infested with
all these buttons, you know, this
ev- every web page, you know, they they
have these badges. You click them to add
them as a browser toolbar. So browser
toolbar is a thing back then, okay? Year
2000. So
year 2000 to 2010, okay? So actually you
can ask AI uh when did it stop?
So anyway, Google Map, you know, these
icons and Google Plus is dead. It was
alive for 10 years or something.
Uh anyway, so web badges, okay.
So, anyway, so I was going to I was
here, web toolbars, okay. So, this
very funny back then.
Uh
So, today you can ask AI to add, you
know, to know
when was uh web toolbars popular? So,
let me ask, okay.
Again, if you are here, say hi, okay.
Post your comments. Now, let me ask um
so
walk
Let me ask in person, I mean, in voice.
Allow voice. Yes.
What's the year period when web toolbars
are popular?
>> Late 1990s to early 2000s. That's when
toolbars flooded Internet Explorer,
often bundled with software or as
adware. Popularity faded with Firefox
and Chrome.
>> When did it die?
>> They faded gradually as Chrome took over
around 2010 to 2016. Chrome didn't
support the old toolbar model, and
extensions replaced them. Google finally
killed its own toolbar in 2021.
>> Fascinating web history. So, I need to
add that to here, so
you know, AI is so helpful. So, because,
you know, before AI, this kind of
questions, like when it popular? It's
hard to
it's hard to web search. You know, you
got Wikipedia who which might talk about
two bars, but
like when did you know,
it's hard to get like the human kind of
like answer. Like when did what what's
the period year period when is very
popular
till it's died. It's hard to get that
kind of answer. Unless you run into a
blog written by human, but then you have
to search, you know, all the blogs.
So, AI is just amazing.
And is the cause of my depression. Okay,
so you got web badge history. So,
anyway, so I'm telling you about this
my page, okay? So, xali.info history of
web tech. Okay, so you got all these
articles.
Okay, I think maybe that's it for today.
Okay, the Time magazine HTML source code
ASCII art. Okay, so that's just funny.
You know, you got this from Time
magazine. When you look at the source
code, control you to look at the source
code. That's how you do it. Then you you
can see they are
Okay, this is just for fun. But for many
website, they when you look at the
source code, they will say like job
available, you know, go there contact,
you know, they they look for web dev.
But let me just mention, for example,
today's like the the way you press
control you to go to a web page to to
see the source code. For example, here's
my page. For example, go back. Go back
to this
um
history of web tech, control you, you
see the
the source code, okay? So, my source
code
which is manual
crafted by hand HTML with love.
Extremely simple and powerful, okay?
Each character
>> [laughter]
>> is crafted by me typed you know one by
one no framework no nothing yet my
workflow
So right now I have like
13,000 HTML articles.
It's faster to write than whatever
framework or static website you use okay
because I have a powerful Emacs system.
I crafted over the past 20 years okay.
So I well I demoed many many times in my
live stream so I'm not going to So
anyway you so so so what I was going to
tell you is that you so you press
control you on Windows or command you on
the Mac to see the source code.
And this is how you learn
HTML.
Okay, so this is how we grew up you know
I mean
since 1990s you know you go to some
website you want you know
how did they do that? Oh you know so you
just control you and you can look at the
source code but today
that is gone okay. So let me show you
okay. So let's go to this great article
a brief history of JavaScript.
You know
written by the Deno people okay look at
the blink funny.
By the way the Deno idiots you know they
they they they changed their logo to
look like a [ __ ]
Can you see? So let me show you that
first okay. So go to Saudi web
Saudi.info okay cuz I talk show cuz I
code Saudi.info
and you scroll down
then you can see and you scroll all the
way down you go pay me okay patreon me
Amazon gift card me.
Does that link still work I hope? Yes
okay. So you can Amazon gift card me or
um
PayPal me, okay?
So, anyway, so you go to the bottom of
my website, then you go to the the um
And what uh yeah, so the you go to here,
then there's a logo design in software
industry. Click there. That's my
collection of commentary on logos of
software industry, okay? And see what I
mean For example, CSS
has a logo now, starting in 2025.
CSS, okay? Official. This is a
official CSS logo, designed by this guy,
okay? So, you can uh his name is Chris
Cook Nielsen. Okay. Anyway, so wait,
wait. Uh okay, so anyway, the official
logo is designed by Javi Aguilar.
But, there's a close um
you know, coming up designed by Chris
Cook Nielsen, which I like better. But,
anyway, the official one is this one,
okay?
>> [snorts]
>> So, CSS got a logo. That's that's news,
okay? In 2025, this year uh last year.
Okay, so and here's a documentation, the
history of the logo, how they designed
it, you know, so I document it.
Okay, you go back to the logo design
software industry page. Uh W3C also got
a logo. I don't know I don't know
if I talked about this on live stream
before, but but before it was W3C.
Very um
serious, you know, the standard
organization for the web. W3 means www3,
3W.
Which stand for World Wide Web.
That's you know, that's what it is. But
today became this
this [ __ ] This wave [ __ ] Like you
don't know what the [ __ ] it is. It's
pretty pretty nothing.
This is the uh
kind of like became the Malaine chain
and Zumas.
>> [laughter]
>> The [snorts] the old one is much better
because it's it got a purpose, you know,
W3C.
W you know, W3 www the World Wide Web. C
is consortium.
You know.
But now it became this crap. And another
thing I want to show you, okay?
Uh God, we digress so much. Um but let
me talk about this. So we want to
validate CSS. So you search for CSS
validator, okay?
Okay, so we digressed a lot. So let me
start to write notes because I don't
want to forget where we talked about. So
let me start to write notes a little
bit, okay?
So we talked about Web Batch.
Okay, we talked about JavaScript history
and history of web tech that link fire
it. Then we were talking about uh
web toolbars history.
Okay. Then we talked about um
Yeah, there is a funny uh Time Magazine
uh code.
Showing showing browser. Fantastic. All
the links are there. So Time Magazine we
were talking about that. There's another
one actually I should link here.
Uh from Facebook where we can Let's
search it.
Uh Facebook
Facebook um
uh
I have quite a few articles on Facebook
because one is one of the most evil
company.
Uh,
Okay, so let's So, so here is another
example.
Wait. Uh,
Facebook browser console warning. Okay,
that's just that's console warning.
Uh, but I was going to show you one
where they
like saying that that
you know, if you are looking for a job,
you know, I think maybe it's not
Facebook. I forgot.
Okay, so anyway, Facebook console
warning, you know, they
stop.
Uh,
anyway, so
Okay, I we got distracted. Okay, hold on
a second. Let me get back to what we
were talking about. So, looking at the
source code, so I want to talk about
looking at the source code. Yeah, source
code.
Looking at HTML source code was how you
learn
it back then. Okay.
>> [snorts]
>> So, source code simple. My website is
simple design and we were talking about.
Yeah, so we started to talk about logos.
Linkify that page.
And go back and this page linkify.
So, why are we talking about logo?
Because we were talking about
Dino.
Dino logo. Okay, let me tell you about
Dino logo. I don't remember if I talked
about this on on live stream, but Dino
logo in 2018, it was this cute Dino
dinos dinosaur. Okay, this one is a
Saurus.
So, what what is the name of the
dinosaur?
What's the name of dino with long necks?
Uh what uh
my dinosaur with long necks? I don't
want that. Just just give me a name like
one name.
God, idiotic.
Brontosaurus,
that's the name. Brontosaurus,
okay? So, Dino logo was like a
Brontosaurus, okay?
But now in 2021, they have Okay, 2021.
So, original 2020A looks like that.
2021 is still Brontosaurus, okay? Looks
like that.
Okay?
I like it I like this. I like that, too,
okay?
But in 2024,
it became this
[ __ ] head.
Penis head.
[ __ ] idiot. 2024, Dino.
That's what it you know, what did What
does that reminds you? It does remind a
lot of people of penis head, okay? It's
a fact.
Then I heard, you know, I post on
Twitter, I heard some someone might you
know, they say, "Oh,
the Ryan Dahl might be a gay." But he
never talked about it, so we don't know.
But you know,
but you know, I mean, even if you gay,
you know, don't don't put that like
that, you know? This What What is it
for?
Like this does this look better than
that?
You know?
So, that's my opinion about logo design,
okay?
So, we were talking about Dino. So,
let's go back to why are we talking
about dinner because
uh because
imagine John Lennon know yeah so we were
talking about John Lennon song before
Let me let's early.
Uh God
>> [sighs]
>> are you guys still with me how many
people watching okay so say hi.
Hi
hi penguin.
Tux
How can someone learn a programming
language you just shut the [ __ ] up you
just learn it okay.
Uh
That's that's what you do just learn it
you got to have desire just learn it.
How can someone learn about you know I
hope you are not a troll but you are a
what a Linux kid.
Linux kid so are you
seriously asking or what what what is
your purpose?
Like when you have a purpose when you
really desire something you know.
You know like how how how do you learn a
language? You don't have to ask.
Okay I think maybe I should stop I
should go join my wife and have dinner.
Abashikadze me traska hi Linux kid yeah
just do it that's right that's correct.
Because you know depends on the person
you don't have to because for me
programming is fantastic because I love
you know because I'm a nerd okay I'm not
good I'm not good with people like
social you know like social butterfly
lots of women females
like that.
That suits them because that benefits
them better even.
But men
are less like that.
So but then but some men are even less
so like me so I'm not good with people
you know I cannot like you know like
be likable you know.
>> [laughter]
>> I'm not a likable person, but I'm good
with thinking, okay? I'm good with
thinking and mathematics, so I love
computers. So, when I do this, oh,
JavaScript, oh, Rust, oh, PowerShell,
oh, Ruby, oh, Python, this it it excites
me, okay?
You don't need to give me money to do
it. I do it for free. It excites me. I
want to know.
Uh Abdol says, Abdol Sam, do you
recommend a lightweight distro to try on
my old laptop, Dell Inspiron? Yes, of
course.
So, of course, uh yeah. So, my favorite
was uh on Linux, my favorite was the
Uh let's show. Uh my favorite was the uh
Um so long, I don't even um
remember the name now. So, my favorite
um
the window the Linux desktop was the uh
I can remember it if I try. So, one of
them is Openbox. That's the most simple,
but it's bundled with the the Openbox
Openbox is a window uh
manager, okay? So-called Windows manager
on Linux, but um the other one is like
the four-letter word. Jesus, let me just
Let me just read my off my blog instead
of me trying to remember, okay? So, hold
on a second, we'll find it in a moment.
Why tiling window manager sucks, that's
my most popular viral article. Okay? So,
we want to go to there. Switch to LXDE
or XFCE.
They are the most lightweight 10 years
ago. I believe still so today, okay? And
they are also my favorite. Doesn't
matter what light or heavy.
You know, I don't want bunch of pretty
[ __ ] like the gnome
or the Ubuntu. You know, I want the
simplest possible. I control everything.
So, if you want a lightweight like save
battery and stuff, LX
LXDE, that's I believe that's the
lightest. And LXDE is created by a
Chinese guy in Taiwan.
Uh believe it or not, I don't know him,
but I from what I've seen, he's kind of
very much a nerd, too, okay? LX LXDE
guy. LXDE was all using a open box, but
now they have a
uh
uh a version based on QT. Anyway, I
haven't been on Linux for a long time,
okay?
So, uh LXDE I can recommend or XFCE,
which I was using for about 6 years on
Linux. I was, you know,
anyway.
i3wm, I guess that, you know, I don't I
haven't used it, but I think that's a
classic, okay?
Okay, so we we digressed far. I need to
get back to what I was talking, okay?
So, let me go back to um
because we digressed far from the So, we
were talking about Dino logo. And before
that, we were talking about why are we
talking about Dino logo? Because we
uh
because yeah, I was going through this
article.
Uh [ __ ] I forgot well, what why are we
uh
talking about it now?
Uh
okay, so yeah, so back then we just look
at the source code. Yeah, remember, look
at the source code, right? So, my
website is so simple, for example. Here
is Kasa info search. Co- control U to
look at the source code. Oh, [ __ ] so
simple. You know, let's say let's go to
uh let's go to Kasa the uh my home page.
You know, my home page
Well, my home page is it's not too
fancy. So, let's go to my JavaScript in
depth. So, you got the side bar. So,
let's go to
some page I have some interactivity. So,
DOM.
So, this is a tutorial for DOM
scripting.
The heart of JavaScript. So, you got
some fancy page. Let's say
>> [groaning]
>> Don't do don't do don't
web scripting examples digital clock.
Okay, that's boring.
So, we got something stopwatch. That's
more boring. Image rollover, that's
boring. Tool tip.
Snow snow effect, okay? It's kind of
fun.
This page is still pretty simple, okay?
So, but you can do control you to learn
how to do it. So, here is the source
code. You can see. Okay.
My web page powerful and simple and all
handcrafted with love.
But now, if you go to a modern website,
let's look let's look at the Deno, you
know, Deno a brief history of
JavaScript. Just an article, that's it.
Nothing else. There's no fancy
interactivity, you know, just an
article.
Control you.
>> [laughter]
>> Jesus my God, what the [ __ ] is this?
Well, actually
this is pretty simple, okay? So, because
Wait, so let me show you, okay? So, you
see
this is the source code
for this page, okay? Just an article,
okay? With some images, okay? Now, you
go to the source code.
Okay, control you. Wait.
Deno, control you source code. Control A
is to select all. Control C to copy.
Now, control Now, switch back to Emacs a
new buffer paste. Wait, did we copy it?
Copy, go back, select all, paste. There
it is, okay? So, you are looking at the
Deno source code. Look look at how
complicated what a complicated [ __ ] it
is.
You see we are at the bottom. Look at
the scroll bar, you see? Now let's go to
the top of the page.
That's what it looks like.
The modern JavaScript, okay? Because of
you know, let's see um
Let's go down. This this is one big lie,
you see?
A brief history of JavaScript Deno, you
see? You go down they got they got the
you know the cards for Facebook, the
cards for Twitter, you see that's that's
that.
That's when you paste the URL for
example, if you paste the URL to
Twitter, it will show pictures, you
know, on Facebook. So, you need this you
need this meta [ __ ]
You know, for example, I can I can make
it. Anyway, so so then you got oh my god
minify JavaScript encrypted, you know,
like not encrypted but um
made it unreadable [ __ ]
And this is from Google. This is Google
Google tracker.
It needs to know every mouse scroll like
when when did you scroll up?
It records everything.
And look at this look at this this part.
What the [ __ ] Um
Okay, let's not get too over excited.
So, um
do that. Yeah, so do that to make them
one line so you can see exactly what
they are. Yeah, incomprehensible [ __ ]
Okay? So, anyway, my what I'm doing here
is just to show you the modern
JavaScript.
Okay, so this is like the modern
JavaScript. Like what the [ __ ] is this?
Let's see. LI is a list item. Class.
Okay, so class So you So you got these
classes.
Uh 20 class. So make them
one on each line. Okay, so press press
press Emacs power. So you got about 10
classes.
And what are these These must be from um
you know that wing
tailwind.
>> [laughter]
>> I uh
Are they tailwind? I don't think they
are uh because they
I don't know because I haven't used tail
tail
uh tailwind.
But we are hiring
a a tailwind engineer with 12 years
experience, okay?
tailwind
tailwind CSS
Okay, I think I'm I've gone crazy. I
think that's it for today. Uh how long
have I been talking for? 1 hour. Okay, 1
hour and 1 minute, okay? So we rambled
all over. So you know, so I think we
should out um
okay?
Anything else?
Let's see. Let me answer the question
and that's it for today.
Have you tried Kachy OS? No. Heard they
have a better
uh support with Nvidia drivers. No, I
don't know what that is.
I tried Arch, Linux Mint, Zorin, Fedora
all had an issue with overheating.
Oh, so you are experienced. You are not
a newbie. So in that case you probably
know better than me.
I don't know.
You know, all I have all I know is the,
you know, the LD
LXD and the the other one.
So, if you try all those, you probably
know Linux better than me.
Okay, I think that's it. I think so the
next
i3 WM should not turn your laptop into a
toaster, otherwise you might need to
re-paste you. Yeah, I think you got some
other problems, probably.
LXD, yes.
Nvidia support is terrible
on Linux. When I run any video on Linux,
it just overheats.
Okay, you mean LXD? I don't know, but
back then I looked at, you know,
like the Linux technology, they are
always backwards. You know, they are
like behind 10 years, you know, like
like like true.
Maybe except the kernel. Like the kernel
is not behind, but everything else, the
GUI, the USB support, the graphic
support, usually it's like 10 years or
five
behind than Mac or Windows. Like every
time there's a new thing.
Like USB 3, you know, just came out or
USB 4 maybe, you know, whatever USB-C.
Like the Linux or you know, or whatever
the
you know, like Linux is always 5 years,
you know, wait for 5 years, then you can
have it.
You know,
then you have a
kernel or whatever compatible with that
or you know,
>> [snorts]
>> so
so you know, so on the on the on the the
Windows system, the graphic system, you
know, you have buffered system, like the
Windows, I don't know what's the
technology, but the the technology to
draw all the windows and you know, your
screen.
On the Mac, back in 20 years ago, you
got something called Aqua. Okay.
I don't know how it works. Okay, I'm
not, you know, the graphics guy. But
anyway, you got the Aqua like the
framework.
On Windows, I I don't know what they
call it, but they got something similar.
Okay.
But on Win on Linux, you got this
You you kind of got it, you know, like
starting 20 years ago with the
you know, the the very popular rotating
cube. What what's that
window manager called, you know? Then
everyone is doing it. [ __ ] stupid.
Like it and transparency. You know, one
thing I hate that Linux people always
do. Like they have transparent terminal.
Transparent terminals. Like the idiot
Linux.
I you know, I don't want my terminal to
be transparent. Okay.
Uh let's see. What am I CD
uh web then Casali
info. Okay, then talk show for example,
today's talk show. Then you can do the
and oh my god.
Okay, do it again. You know.
So the the Linux people, they they they
they have like they have transparent You
you can set that on on a PowerShell,
too, you know? I mean, this is the
Windows terminal I'm using the Windows
terminal. You can You can actually set
it to transparent.
The Linux idiots, they have transparent
terminal. Impossible to see. Like [ __ ]
with your vision. Like if I'm doing
work, I want to see, you know, if I go
to terminal, I want to see exactly the
text on terminal. I don't want to see
what's in the background. Oh my god, the
Linux idiots. They like they have like
They have double penetrating eyes. Like
they have to see this screen, but they
also need to see what's behind it, like
[ __ ] Linux idiots.
You know, the Linux rising and Arch
Linux and
or you know, the the the the Gentoo or
Gentoo Linux, you know, these idiots.
They like they always have that
transparency, [ __ ]
I don't have nothing transparent. In In
fact, even on Windows I banned it.
Like Like you can go through like I I
turned it off. I don't want anything
transparent, okay? Idiot.
But the Linux
transparency transparent terminal they
have. Oh my god, my terminal is
transparent.
[ __ ] idiots.
Uh so, okay, I'm done today, okay?
Catchy Linux, I don't know what what is
Catchy. I never heard of it.
Catchy, uh is it Catchy OS? Uh Catchy
OS.
Catchy OS, huh?
Linux distro Catchy OS, let's look at
the Wikipedia. Let's see what it says.
Uh
here.
Okay, a new kid in town.
Uh this article has multiple issues.
Please improve. That usually means
>> [laughter]
>> the the people is spanning the
you know, he's trying to edit the the
page like
into [ __ ] Some of these articles list
of sources may not be reliable, okay?
This article may contain improper
references, okay? So this this means
you know, like I never heard of it. So
and with these warnings, it it means
this this
you know, they are trying to promote it.
They they you know, they are you know,
the people they are Catchy OS, they are
trying to put things. Oh, how great we
are.
Oh, we beat everything.
Popularity ranking, look.
>> [laughter]
>> They have to have a popularity ranking.
Of course, it's good, isn't it? CentOS
attracted increased attention from the
Linux community press through 2024 and
2025 as its ranking on DistroWatch's
page hit statistics rose sharply
culminating at
taking the top position on that ranking
in mid-2025.
Oh, Jesus. [ __ ]
What is the what MX Linux?
You know, MX Linux
was created by Apple in 1990s
eight.
But uh but I guess they reused, you
know, someone reused the name. Wait, was
it MX Linux? No.
I think so.
So, okay, again, let me let me answer
that.
MX Linux, okay, I'm not talking about
that. I'm talking about from Apple.
From Apple 1998.
Oh, that's MK Linux, I forgot. That's
that that this is my first Linux, MK
Linux 1998, okay?
This is a first Linux I installed on
Apple
iMac that
Bondi blue iMac. Do you guys know what's
a Bondi blue iMac? You guys don't know,
okay.
So, let me show it.
Cosnadi keyboard blog, you go to and you
go to search and you search b o n d i
Apple Bondi blue iMac keyboard. So,
I got this computer iMac at work, but I
also got one personally. I got a pink
one. Okay, colorful, fantastic, lovely.
This is 1998. And my first Linux is
installed on this machine, not this one,
though. This photo
uh this photo is not mine, okay? I don't
think it's mine, okay? I don't have a
photo, but you know
but this keyboard this photo is mine.
This is this was my keyboard, okay?
Apple Bondi blue iMac keyboard and mouse
1998, okay?
This photo is not mine, okay? But this
one is.
So anyway, so I installed MX Linux on
this on the on this iMac, okay? 1998.
So anyway, MX Linux, I don't know. Let's
go back. So let's see what is this
Catchy OS. Catchy OS is a rolling
release Linux distribution based on Arch
Linux. I focus on performance
optimization and unstable Okay, I don't
think I care.
Just crap. Well, I can maybe it's good,
okay? But I
Uh [sighs] okay. So no, I have not heard
of it.
Okay, bye guys.
But nowadays, Mac and Windows is trying
to match Linux.
>> [laughter]
>> No, give me a break.
My terminal is white on red.
White on red. Hmm, that's interesting.
That's interesting, though, because red
is a good color for the eye, okay?
That's biology. So let's see, can we
control shift T?
So let's see if I can create a um um
Okay, let's just go. Let's see if I can
Just just let's just play with it, okay?
So, you go to settings. Um
Can you magnify this? Okay.
You know, I hate it when you cannot
magnify every every UI. Because right
now I want to do the live stream, and
you go to this settings page, you guys
cannot see. It's too small, but
Let's see. Control
Scroll up. No, it doesn't work. Control
plus
[ __ ] idiot. You see, so it's too
small, you know. You guys You guys
cannot see, and you cannot magnify it.
So, this is idiocy, okay?
It's kind of Oh, you you got all sort of
the idiocies, okay?
So, color scheme
Okay, I don't want to bother. I don't
want to bother um
Add new. Actually, I can quickly add
new.
Uh color scheme 16
So, colors foreground foreground
background red. Let's see what happens.
Background red.
Okay.
What?
Uh can you save what?
Okay. Oh.
Oh.
Oh. Oh.
Okay, let's try that.
Okay.
Uh
save.
So, columns color scheme 16. Can you
save the name? So, how do I
Um rename color. Okay, rename.
Color
X red.
Okay.
Now
Go back here.
Magnify.
Can you make it color scheme?
No. Oh, what?
Ah, very annoying. Let's see new. No.
Okay, so set as default.
Can you make one tab just to use this?
No, in that you have to um
Yeah, I don't care, you know. I don't
play change tab color. No.
Uh annoying, okay.
So, you if you set default, then I have
to set it back later. Oh, let's just why
not?
Set as default. Save, okay.
Now, new. Okay, there.
So, I want to go to
Xerox.
Web
Okay, now magnify.
Massive.
Duh.
Okay, not bad.
Okay.
Okay, bye guys.
Was it NeXT made by Steve Jobs
independently?
Yes.
Steve Jobs got created Apple, then he
got kicked out.
Doing power struggle
by the John Sculley guy.
You know, so pretty sad, you know, he
founded the company, but you know, but
he's he, you know, he he
Anyway, so they they got a power
struggle and they kicked him out because
he he's, you know, he's not
very likable. I I guess some some you
know,
uh so
so he created then he founded NeXT and
also he founded um
Pixar. So, Steve Jobs is a very
successful entrepreneur, a businessman.
He's got a vision. He's very successful.
He's very capable. So, he got kicked
kicked out by Apple, you know,
power struggle, you know, the board, you
know, they kicked him out. But then he
uh
he created NeXT computer and Pixar,
which, you know,
which created the animation, you know,
Toy Toys uh
story, lots of very succe- successful,
Nemo and so on.
And he created NeXT computer. NeXT
computer kind of failed, but so in but
in 2019 uh in in in in year 1990, around
1997, he came back to Apple because
Apple at that time is dying.
Is dying.
And uh um they and Apple operating
system crashes literally every day
because I was using it every day. It
crashes every day, more than one time.
So, Apple is trying to create a new
operating system named Copland, but
it didn't work I mean it it it it it's
not working, you know.
So, they are looking you know, they are
possibly thinking of buying some other
operating system.
Then there are two options. One is from
BeOS.
The other one is from NeXT, NeXT
computer, okay.
So, can I show you some
some articles? Yes, I can. So, let me
hold on a second. So, I want to show
that, keep that, okay. So, n e x t, so
you can see NeXT computer, okay. NeXT
keyboard.
And let me show you something else,
okay. Actually, I should go, okay. So,
okay, few in fact 3 more minutes, okay.
So, actually, I want to show you
something
Let's let's search for NeXT Computer
Inc., okay.
And then there is BOS, okay.
So, NeXT Computer Inc. That's Steve
Jobs. And let's go to
BOS. Do I have independent article? No.
Okay, so
So, Apple is dying because in around
1997 because the
Mac OS is old, crashes every day.
And uh
So, they have two options. One is buy
buy from BOS. This is a new operating
system. It's
you know, back then.
And also hardware
from one of the, you know, it was
created by Jean-Louis Gassée.
How you pronounce it, I don't know. A
French guy, I suppose. He was an Apple
employee, but he left to create his new
brand new vision. Because at that time,
1996,
you know, we have multimedia, which is a
new thing. So, they want a new operating
system system from the ground up
designed for multimedia,
you know, videos and voice, you know. At
that, you know, it's it was cutting
edge. You know, today you think, oh,
maybe it's silly. Linux, [ __ ] Linux.
[ __ ] the Linux idiots.
1996, okay? That's when Linux was
cooking, okay? So, anyway, so they
wanted, you know, like you have you
know, they want from start from scratch
because multimedia is new thing, you
know, you need new thinking about
operating system. So, the BeOS, okay,
they began. They also created hardware,
okay?
So, Apple has a choice to buy from Be or
Steve Jobs, the very smart guy, the
salesman.
Uh
you know, he created BeOS. I mean, the
he Steve Jobs created NeXT. So, here's a
NeXT keyboard.
Okay, so let's see if I can magnify this
and move this up.
NeXT computer, okay? NeXT computer is
beautiful, very expensive back then.
Like you can't afford it, you know, you
um
and Mathematica Wolfram Language came
with it, actually.
From the you know, this looks like that,
huge and and beautiful, okay?
Uh high quality, highest quality and and
fairly powerful.
So, Steve Jobs created that when he got
kicked out by Apple. And
so, Apple is buying a want to buy a new
operating system and Steve Jobs come
back and saying, "Look, you can buy my
NeXT operating system."
So, Steve Jobs So, Apple bought it.
It's a great story because BeOS offered
Apple much cheaper.
Apple bought Steve Jobs NeXT OS,
paid much more.
And
after that, Steve Jobs basically took
over.
He was He was known as interim CEO, but
basically he just became, you know, he
just run Apple again.
Then he saved Apple from death
because Apple was dying.
You know, the the CEO the from Pepsi
Corporation John Sculley, they don't
know how to run things. Apple is dying.
Without Steve Jobs, Apple is dying.
You know, then Steve Jobs, the first
thing he did is iMac.
Amazing innovation.
Steve Jobs, one of the greatest
businessman, salesman, and innovator.
Okay, entrepreneur. He knows how to do
it. He he's got the vision. Look at this
computer is great.
Okay, and uh this uh mouse, you know.
The first thing, USB. The first computer
kind kind of the first computer with
USB.
You know, the the screw that, you know,
before USB was the, you know, other code
um PS5 or something.
Or PS2. But anyway, Apple, okay, and CD
drive. Okay.
That's it. Bye, guys. Um
So, yeah, so Next may drop independent,
okay? It has to be reopened, I think. It
has to be reopened. Heard what?
Uh
Rising Linux. Rising Linux, yeah. I want
just solid background. My terminal is
way on red. Okay, bye.
Uh shutting down shutting down in 1
minute. Okay, I'm going to have dinner.
Thanks for watching. Cheers. Tonight's
drink is a power juice.
Next computer I've seen, but I never
used. I never touched it. I never tried
it. However, I do have the keyboard.
The next keyboard I bought at that at
one time.
Uh
was it? Did I bought it or I I it free?
I forgot. But I had the keyboard for a
while. Yeah,
I don't remember what I did with it. I
think I gave it away or something or
threw it away. But,
that Yeah, anyway.
Okay, that's a lot. Uh bye, guys.